<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>luispe – Reflection</title><link>https://luispe.github.io/blog/tags/reflection/</link><description>Recent content in Reflection on luispe</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 19:10:20 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://luispe.github.io/blog/tags/reflection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Ticket Hell</title><link>https://luispe.github.io/blog/posts/ticket-hell/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 19:10:20 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://luispe.github.io/blog/posts/ticket-hell/</guid><description>
&lt;h2&gt;Problem&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="problem"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#problem" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I start with this well-known phrase?
First, I want to give a bit of background, and then I’ll explain why I mention it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years working with infrastructure teams, I’ve had the great fortune of meeting some very insightful people who have always told me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Never let the infrastructure team operate solely through ticket requests.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Position&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="position"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#position" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What’s the rationale behind such a strong stance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need an &lt;strong&gt;extremely strong culture&lt;/strong&gt; from end to end to decide which ticket is more important than another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure team must inherently grow&lt;/strong&gt; as the tech and product teams expand to new features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s &lt;strong&gt;extremely difficult to keep the infrastructure team motivated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation is impossible&lt;/strong&gt; in a ticket-driven infrastructure model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other reasons, but these are the most relevant ones — let’s go through each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Extremely Strong Culture&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="1-extremely-strong-culture"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#1-extremely-strong-culture" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure and QA teams are rarely included in roadmap and sprint planning.
If they are, it usually happens at the very end — “when everything’s already cooked.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when the infrastructure lead receives two tickets and needs to prioritize based on execution capacity, the obvious question arises:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which ticket should I prioritize?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck with that — because for every internal team (your “clients”), their request will always be &lt;strong&gt;the most important thing in the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Meaningless Growth&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="2-meaningless-growth"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#2-meaningless-growth" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume the previous issue is somehow solved.
You still can’t escape this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we say the infrastructure team &lt;em&gt;must inherently grow&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you fall into the pattern of having infrastructure handle all ticket requests, then as the company launches more products and features, you’ll need &lt;strong&gt;more infrastructure engineers&lt;/strong&gt; to handle the growing ticket demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations — you’ve created an &lt;strong&gt;execution bottleneck.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The “solution”?&lt;/strong&gt; Hire more infrastructure people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Motivation&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="3-motivation"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#3-motivation" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume points 1 and 2 are solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip; are infrastructure engineers human?
(They are, last I checked.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to stay motivated in a role that &lt;strong&gt;should be driven by creativity&lt;/strong&gt; but instead is reduced to &lt;strong&gt;just closing tickets&lt;/strong&gt; — with no room for questioning or discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens next?
High turnover in the infrastructure team and growing frustration among product or tech teams.
And if those teams happen to be toxic, they might even start labeling infrastructure as &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;a blocker.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what can I say about that?
&lt;strong&gt;Keep calm — and here’s a big hug.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Innovation&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="4-innovation"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#4-innovation" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, even if the previous three points were somehow resolved, &lt;strong&gt;innovation is still impossible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?
Because a team that only closes tickets — that only participates reactively in projects to “build infrastructure” — &lt;strong&gt;will never have the space to innovate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back to the Beginning&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="back-to-the-beginning"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#back-to-the-beginning" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this post, I’ve explained the reasoning and main consequences of running infrastructure management through tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I want to be clear:
Working &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; tickets in an infrastructure team isn’t necessarily wrong.
&lt;strong&gt;What’s absolutely wrong is managing infrastructure and platform operations &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; tickets.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does the “hammer” metaphor have to do with this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means that many companies &lt;strong&gt;misapplied agile methodologies&lt;/strong&gt; to their infrastructure teams.
It’s time to &lt;strong&gt;pause and reflect&lt;/strong&gt; on why things aren’t working well in so many places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can we avoid it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must &lt;strong&gt;inject a product mindset into infrastructure teams&lt;/strong&gt; — offering &lt;strong&gt;high-quality abstractions and user experiences&lt;/strong&gt; over the underlying platform chaos, enabling product engineering teams to become &lt;strong&gt;self-sufficient&lt;/strong&gt; in managing their software and its infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope my experience helps you rethink how to build culture and work processes for infrastructure teams within your company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or want to discuss any of this, I’d love to connect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you soon! 👋🏽&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Technical debt</title><link>https://luispe.github.io/blog/posts/technical-debt/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 16:36:17 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://luispe.github.io/blog/posts/technical-debt/</guid><description>
&lt;p&gt;In the following post we will rethink a concept commonly encountered and endorsed
in the technology industry, technical debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Different yardstick&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="different-yardstick"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#different-yardstick" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine that we need to paint the exterior of our house, and we decide to hire a professional to do the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After consulting several quotes we decided to hire the services of &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo; to take care of the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few days &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo; tells us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- The work is finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stood at the front of the house and noticed that around the window frames it is unpainted in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noticing this, we ask &amp;ldquo;x&amp;rdquo; why he did not paint around the window frames, to which he responds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Sorry, it is a technical debt that I can attack in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would you feel if you encountered such a situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why in the context of technology do we endorse having technical debt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rethink&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="rethink"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#rethink" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In technology, it is very common to encounter this scenario, and unfortunately we naturalize it and as
I commented in a &lt;a href="https://luispe.github.io/blog/posts/mistakes-and-learnings/"target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;previous publication&lt;/a&gt;
where I talk among other things about the importance of documenting and testing, it is something common that
I always see as &amp;ldquo;technical debt&amp;rdquo;, rethinking the example of painting the house I think it exposes
how we can have &amp;ldquo;different yardsticks&amp;rdquo; to measure the same situation in different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is technical debt harmful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In test context: it is extremely difficult to make changes without exploding everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In context of documentation: it is extremely difficult to add functionality because the lack of
documentation causes us to waste an enormous amount of time trying to understand how things are built.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a team context: having technical debt means that the knowledge stays with the people and we should always,
always encourage knowledge to be distributed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;span class="hx:absolute hx:-mt-20" id="conclusions"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="#conclusions" class="subheading-anchor" aria-label="Permalink for this section"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The technical debt is very exhausting for the teams and where today we think we are gaining time,
I assure you that soon, very soon, we will lose agility and speed in the development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be avoided in most cases, and we do not accept it as a matter of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I hope that we will rethink together the &amp;ldquo;technical debt&amp;rdquo; and that we will be uncomfortable with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading! 👋🏽&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>